you pick up the phone, you can guess or predict what this phone call is about. It's because of an injection of intelligence into a process which was considered dead for a long time in the West. And the last kind of innovation, invisible innovation coming out of India is what we call management innovation. It's not a new product or a new process but a new way to organize work, and the most significant management innovation to come out of India, invented by the Indian offshoring industry is what we call the global delivery model. What the global delivery model allows is, it allows you to take previously geographically core-located tasks, break them up into parts, send them around the world where the expertise and the cost structure exists, and then specify the means for reintegrating them. Without that, you could not have any of the other invisible innovations today. So, what I'm trying to say is, what we are finding in our research is, that if products for end users is the visible tip of the innovation iceberg, India is well represented in the invisible, large, submerged portion of the innovation iceberg. Now, this has, of course, some implications, and so we developed three implications of this research. The first is what we called sinking skill ladder, and now I'm going to go back to where I started my conversation with you, which was about the flight of jobs. Now, of course, when we first, as a multinational company, decide to outsource jobs to India in the R&amp;D, what we are going to do is we are going to outsource the bottom rung of the ladder to India, the least sophisticated jobs, just like Tom Friedman would predict. Now, what happens is, when you outsource the bottom rung of the ladder to India for innovation and for R&amp;D work, at some stage in the very near future you are going to have to confront a problem, which is where does the next step of the ladder people come from within your company? So you have two choices then: Either you bring the people from India into the developed world to take positions in the next step of the ladder — immigration — or you say, there's so many people in the bottom step of the ladder waiting to take the next position in India, why don't we move the next step to India? What we are trying to say is that once you outsource the bottom end of the ladder, you -- it's a self-perpetuating act, because of the sinking skill ladder, and the sinking skill ladder is simply the point that you can't be an investment banker without having been an analyst once. You can't be a professor without having been a student. You can't be a consultant without having been a research associate. So, if you outsource the least sophisticated jobs, at some stage, the next step of the ladder has to follow. The second thing we bring up is what we call the browning of the TMT, the top management teams. If the R&amp;D talent is going to be based out of India and China, and the largest growth markets are going to be based out of India and China, you have to confront the problem that your top management of the future is going to have to come out of India and China, because that's where the product leadership is, that's where the important market leadership is. Right? And the last thing we point out in this slide, which is, you know, that to this story, there's one caveat. India has the youngest growing population in the world. This demographic dividend is incredible, but paradoxically, there's also the mirage of mighty labor pools. Indian institutes and educational system, with a few exceptions, are incapable of producing students in the quantity and quality needed to keep this innovation engine going, so companies are finding innovative ways to overcome this, but in the end it does not absolve the government of the responsibility for creating this educational structure. So finally, I want to conclude by showing you the profile of one company, IBM. As many of you know, IBM has always been considered for the last hundred years to be one of the most innovative companies. In fact, if you look at the number of patents filed over history, I think they are in the top or the top two or three companies in the world of all patents filed in the USA as a private company. Here is the profile of employees of IBM over the last decade. In 2003, they had 300,000 employees, or 330,000 employees, out of which, 135,000 were in America, 9,000 were in India. In 2009, they had 400,000 employees, by which time the U.S. employees had moved to 105,000, whereas the Indian employees had gone to 100,000. Well, in 2010, they decided they're not going to reveal this data anymore, so I had to make some estimates based on various sources. Here are my best guesses. Okay? I'm not saying this is the exact number, it's my best guess. It gives you a sense of the trend. There are 433,000 people now at IBM, out of which 98,000 are remaining in the U.S., and 150,000 are in India. So you tell me, is IBM an American company, or an Indian company? (Laughter) Ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much. (Applause)
antes de contestar el teléfono, se puede adivinar o predecir qué se va a tratar en la llamada. Esto se debe a una inyección de inteligencia al proceso, que estaba considerando muerto en Occidente desde hace tiempo. Y el último tipo de innovación, innovación invisible de la India es lo que llamamos gestión de innovación. No son productos o procesos nuevos sino una nueva forma de organizar el trabajo y la gestión de innovación más relevante de la India, inventada por la industria de subcontratos al exterior hindú, que llamamos modelo de entrega global. El modelo de entrega global permite tomar tareas centrales previamente asignadas geográficamente, separarlas en partes que se envían alrededor del mundo donde tengan la experiencia y la estructura de costos para luego especificar los medios y reintegralos. Sin esto, no podrían tener ninguna de las innovaciones invisibles actuales. Lo que intento decir, lo que hemos hallado en nuestra investigación es que si los productos para usuarios finales son la punta visible del iceberg de la innovación, India está bien representada en la gran e invisible porción sumergida del iceberg de la innovación. Por supuesto, esto tiene algunas implicaciones, tres de las cuales estudiamos en esta investigación. La primera es la que llamamos la escalera de habilidad sumergida, y ahora voy a regresar al inicio de mi charla sobre la fuga de cerebros. Por supuesto, en un inicio, como una compañía multinacional, decidimos subcontratar la I+D a la India, lo que íbamos a hacer era subcontratar el peldaño más bajo de la escalera a la India, los trabajos menos sofisticados justo como Tom Friedman lo predijera. Entonces lo que sucede cuando subcontratas el peldaño más bajo de la escalera de la innovación y la I+D a la India, es que llega un momento en el futuro cercano donde tienes que confrontar un problema: ¿de dónde viene la gente del siguiente paso de la escalera dentro de la compañía? Tienen entonces dos opciones: ya sea que lleven a la gente de la India al mundo desarrollado y ocupe puestos en el siguiente paso de la escalera -inmigración- o bien, hay tanta gente en el peldaño más bajo de la escalera esperando el siguiente puesto en la India, que ¿por qué no mover el siguiente peldaño a la India? Lo que intentamos decir es que una vez que subcontratas el peldaño más bajo de la escalera, se vuelve un acto de auto perpetuación, por la simple razón de que en la escalera de habilidad sumergida no puedes ser un banquero inversionista sin haber sido alguna vez un analista. No puedes ser un profesor sin haber sido un estudiante. No puedes ser un consultor sin haber sido un investigador asociado. Entonces si subcontratas los trabajos menos sofisticados, llega el momento de tomar el siguiente paso de la escalera. La segunda cosa por mencionar es lo que llamamos el bronceado de los equipos de alta gerencia TMT (en inglés). Si el talento de I+D se va a ubicar fuera de la India y China, y los mercados en crecimiento más grandes van a estar en la India y China, tienen que confrontar el problema de que su alta dirección del futuro provendrá de la India y China, porque es allí donde está el liderazgo de producto, donde está el liderazgo de mercado importante. ¿Cierto? Y la última cosa que resaltamos en esta diapositiva, es que esta historia tiene una advertencia. India tiene la población más joven en crecimiento del mundo. Esta cuota demográfica es increíble y a la vez paradójica, también tiene el espejismo de grupos de labor poderosos, instituciones hindúes y sistema educativo, salvo algunas excepciones, incapaces de producir estudiantes en cantidades y calidades que mantengan funcionando esta máquina de innovación. Así las compañías están encontrando innovaciones para superar esto, pero al final esto no absuelve al gobierno de la responsabilidad de crear la estructura educacional. Por último quiero concluir mostrándoles el perfil de una compañía, IBM. Como muchos de Uds. saben, IBM ha sido siempre considerada una de las compañías más innovadoras en los últimos cien años. De hecho si miran la historia del número de patentes solicitadas creo que están entre las dos o tres a la cabeza en el mundo de todas las patentes solicitas en Estados Unidos por una compañía privada. Aquí está el perfil de empleados de IBM en la última década. En 2003, tenían 300 000 empleados, de los cuales, 135 000 eran de los Estados Unidos y 9000 de la India. En 2009, tenían 400 000 empleados, de los cuales de Estados Unidos se redujeron a 105 000, mientras que de la India subieron a 100 000. Para el 2010, decidieron ya no publicar más los datos, así que tuve que hacer algunas estimaciones con base a varias fuentes. Esta es mi mejor estimación ¿sí? No estoy diciendo que sea una cifra exacta, es mi mejor estimación; da una idea de la tendencia. IBM tiene ahora 433 000 empleados, de los que 98 000 son de Estados Unidos y 150 000 son de la India. Díganme entonces, ¿es IBM una compañía estadounidense o una compañía hindú? (Risas) Damas y caballeros, muchas gracias (Aplausos)